<numericalExperiment ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment"><canonicalName>ssp5-85ext</canonicalName><description>What: Long-term extension, beyond 2100,  for the SSP5-8.5 scenario.   Emissions are eventually reduced to a level that is found to produce equilibrated radiative forcing at a relatively high level by 2300 in a simple climate model. Concentration-driven. 
Why: To investigate long term changes associated with a high forcing scenario.</description><keywords><keyword>Scenario</keyword><keyword>SSP</keyword><keyword>RCP</keyword><keyword>SSP5</keyword><keyword>RCP8.5 extension</keyword><keyword>future</keyword><keyword>climate change</keyword><keyword>IPCC</keyword><keyword>ScenarioMIP</keyword><keyword>SSP-based RCP</keyword><keyword>Tier 2</keyword></keywords><longName>SSP5-8.5 extension</longName><meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocMetaInfo"><authorReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><uid>253825f3-fbc8-43fb-b1f6-cc575dc693eb</uid><version>1</version></authorReference><createDate>2015-11-24 20:47:12.037121</createDate><id>8e46da76-ead2-4497-b155-76588855d7fd</id><institute>--</institute><language>en</language><project>cmip6-draft</project><source>spreadsheet</source><type>cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment</type><updateDate>2015-11-24 20:47:12.037121</updateDate><version>1</version></meta><name>SSP5-85ext</name><references><reference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Citation"><abstract>This paper describes the scenario matrix architecture that underlies a framework for developing new scenarios for climate change research. The matrix architecture facilitates addressing key questions related to current climate research and policy-making: identifying the effectiveness of different adaptation and mitigation strategies (in terms of their costs, risks and other consequences) and the possible trade-offs and synergies. The two main axes of the matrix are: 1) the level of radiative forcing of the climate system (as characterised by the representative concentration pathways) and 2) a set of alternative plausible trajectories of future global development (described as shared socio-economic pathways). The matrix can be used to guide scenario development at different scales. It can also be used as a heuristic tool for classifying new and existing scenarios for assessment. Key elements of the architecture, in particular the shared socio-economic pathways and shared policy assumptions (devices for incorporating explicit mitigation and adaptation policies), are elaborated in other papers in this special issue.</abstract><citationStr>van Vuuren DP, Kriegler E, O’Neill BC, Ebi KL, Riahi K, Carter TR, Edmonds J, Hallegatte S, Kram T, Mathur R, Winkler H (2014) A new scenario framework for Climate Change Research: scenario matrix architecture. Climatic Change, Special Issue, Nakicenovic N, Lempert R, Janetos A (eds) A Framework for the Development of New Socioeconomic Scenarios for Climate Change Research.</citationStr><context>Describes combining SSPs with radiative forcing.</context><doi>10.1007/s10584-013-0906-1</doi><title>A new scenario framework for Climate Change Research: scenario matrix architecture.</title><url ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.OnlineResource"><description>Describes combining SSPs with radiative forcing</description><linkage>http://rd.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10584-013-0906-1</linkage><name>vanVuuren et al. 2014</name><protocol>http</protocol></url></reference><reference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Citation"><abstract>The new scenario framework for climate change research envisions combining pathways of future radiative forcing and their associated climate changes with alternative pathways of socioeconomic development in order to carry out research on climate change impacts, adaptation, and mitigation. Here we propose a conceptual framework for how to define and develop a set of Sharted Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs) for use within the scenario framework.  We define SSPs as reference pathways describing plausible alternative trends in the evolution of society and ecosystems over a century timescale, in the absence of climate change or climate policies.  We introduce the concept of a space of challenges to adaptation and to mitigation that should be spanned by the SSPs, and discuss how particular trends in social, economic, and environmental development could be combined to produce such outcomes.  A comparison to the narratives from the scenarios developed in the Special Report on Emission Scenarios (SRES) illustrates how a starting point for developing SSPs can be defined.  We suggest initial development of a set of basic SSPs that could then be extended to meet more specific purposes, and envision a process of application of basic and extended SSPs that would be iterative and potentially lead to modification of the original SSPs themselves.</abstract><citationStr>O'Neill, B., Kriegler, E., Riahi, K., Ebi, K.L., Hallegatte, S., Carter, T.R., Mathur, R. and D.P. van Vuuren, 2014: A new scenario framework for climate change research: the concept of shared socioeconomic pathways. Climate change, Special Issue, Nakicenovic N, Lempert R, Janetos A (eds) A Framework for the Development of New Socioeconomic Scenarios for Climate Change Research.</citationStr><context>Describes Shared Socioeconomc Pathways (SSPs) 1-5</context><doi>10.1007/s10584-013-0905-2</doi><title>A new scenario framework for climate change research: the concept of shared socioeconomic pathways</title><url ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.OnlineResource"><description>Description of the SSPs 1-5</description><linkage>http://rd.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10584-013-0905-2</linkage><name>O'Neill et al. 2014</name><protocol>http</protocol></url></reference><reference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Citation"><abstract>A collection of proposal documents from MIPs making the case for their inclusion in CMIP6.</abstract><citationStr>Overview CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs</citationStr><context>Describes the MIPs contributing to CMIP6</context><doi>N/A</doi><title>Overview CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs</title><url ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.OnlineResource"><description>A collection of proposal documents from MIPs making the case for their inclusion in CMIP6.</description><linkage>http://wcrp-climate.org/images/modelling/WGCM/CMIP/CMIP6-EndorsedMIPs_Summary_150819_Sent.pdf</linkage><name>Overview CMIP6-Endorsed MIPs</name><protocol>http</protocol></url></reference></references><relatedExperimentsReferences><relatedExperimentsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>86f70ce3-c15f-46b4-8aa4-366956fcfcd8</id><type>cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment</type><version>1</version></relatedExperimentsReference><relatedExperimentsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>569c8088-2de7-4bbc-9295-8a3d306303a5</id><type>cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment</type><version>1</version></relatedExperimentsReference><relatedExperimentsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>a43b07dc-b549-45f1-9a04-b676bb13bc62</id><type>cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment</type><version>1</version></relatedExperimentsReference></relatedExperimentsReferences><requirementsReferences><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>bd8d6625-a2ec-4e7e-80ce-c2303ced589d</id><type>cim.2.designing.TemporalConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>71418864-ab6a-417a-ae20-81b11514127a</id><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>844b94ca-b4cc-4bb2-b878-8fb33696dd1c</id><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>9a6c5616-b270-4153-8d4d-165c794e2bc2</id><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>d089d481-06a4-43f9-9a5e-812588baffac</id><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>ec8105ad-eff3-4030-b144-9c92eca5d953</id><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference></requirementsReferences><responsibleParties><responsibleParty ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Responsibility"><partyReferences><partyReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>40825f03-5985-4719-9899-805c894b6dee</id><type>cim.2.shared.Party</type><version>1</version></partyReference><partyReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>2441a7d0-d549-4495-a8ee-32974c5e5a40</id><type>cim.2.shared.Party</type><version>1</version></partyReference><partyReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>0592421f-1a8b-4362-b049-256f1610df65</id><type>cim.2.shared.Party</type><version>1</version></partyReference></partyReferences><roleCode>point of contact:</roleCode></responsibleParty></responsibleParties></numericalExperiment>