<numericalExperiment ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment"><canonicalName>abrupt4XCO2</canonicalName><description>What:  Impose an instantaneous quadrupling of the concentration of atmospheric carbon dioxide, then hold fixed.

Why: To evaluate the equilibrium climate sensitivity of the model and to diagnose the strength of various feedbacks.</description><keywords><keyword>4x</keyword><keyword>CO2</keyword><keyword>4xCO2</keyword><keyword>instant</keyword><keyword>instantaneous</keyword><keyword>quadrupling</keyword><keyword>ipcc</keyword><keyword>climate</keyword><keyword>deck</keyword></keywords><longName>Abrupt quadrupling of the atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide</longName><meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocMetaInfo"><authorReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><uid>253825f3-fbc8-43fb-b1f6-cc575dc693eb</uid><version>1</version></authorReference><createDate>2015-11-24 20:47:07.603069</createDate><id>f0899933-0056-4b3b-b2e4-3eb653725d80</id><institute>--</institute><language>en</language><project>cmip6-draft</project><source>spreadsheet</source><type>cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment</type><updateDate>2015-11-24 20:47:07.603069</updateDate><version>1</version></meta><name>Abrupt 4XCO2</name><references><reference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Citation"><abstract>The global temperature rose by 0.2°C between the middle 1960's and 1980, yielding a warming of 0.4°C in the past century. This temperature increase is consistent with the calculated greenhouse effect due to measured increases of atmospheric carbon dioxide. Variations of volcanic aerosols and possibly solar luminosity appear to be primary causes of observed fluctuations about the mean trend of increasing temperature. It is shown that the anthropogenic carbon dioxide warming should emerge from the noise level of natural climate variability by the end of the century, and there is a high probability of warming in the 1980's. Potential effects on climate in the 21st century include the creation of drought-prone regions in North America and central Asia as part of a shifting of climatic zones, erosion of the West Antarctic ice sheet with a consequent worldwide rise in sea level, and opening of the fabled Northwest Passage.</abstract><citationStr>Hansen, J., D. Johnson, A. Lacis, S. Lebedeff, P. Lee, D. Rind, and G. Russell, 1981: Climate impact of increasing atmospheric carbon dioxide. Science, 213, 957-96.</citationStr><context>The paper cited here describes an abrupt increase to 2XCO2 concentration, nevertheless it is the first abrupt CO2 experiment to be described in the literature and provides excellent context.</context><doi>10.1126/science.213.4511.957</doi><title>Climate Impact of Increasing Atmospheric Carbon Dioxide</title><url ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.OnlineResource"><description>The original abrupt CO2 increase paper</description><linkage>http://www.sciencemag.org/content/213/4511/957.short</linkage><name>Hansen et al. 1981</name><protocol>http</protocol></url></reference><reference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Citation"><abstract>Since 1995, the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) has coordinated climate model experiments involving multiple international modeling teams. Through CMIP, climate modelers and scientists from around the world have analyzed and compared state-of-the-art climate model simulations to gain insights into the processes, mechanisms, and consequences of climate variability and climate change. This has led to a better understanding of past, present, and future climate, and CMIP model experiments have routinely been the basis for future climate change assessments made by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) [e.g., IPCC, 2013, and references therein].</abstract><citationStr>Meehl, G. A., R. Moss, K. E. Taylor, V. Eyring, R. J. Stouffer, S. Bony, B. Stevens, 2014: Climate Model Intercomparisons: Preparing for the Next Phase, Eos Trans. AGU, 95(9), 77.</citationStr><context>Overview of the CMIP6</context><doi>10.1002/2014EO090001</doi><title>Climate Model Intercomparisons: Preparing for the Next Phase</title><url ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.OnlineResource"><description>Overview of the CMIP6</description><linkage>http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/2014EO090001/epdf</linkage><name>Meehl et al. 2014</name><protocol>http</protocol></url></reference></references><relatedExperimentsReferences><relatedExperimentsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>9f79fe87-5a7a-4aa1-a58c-f1efa68974e9</id><type>cim.2.designing.NumericalExperiment</type><version>1</version></relatedExperimentsReference></relatedExperimentsReferences><requirementsReferences><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>329c0aed-631e-4585-837b-5a384d7b035d</id><type>cim.2.designing.TemporalConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference><requirementsReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>3c297d73-944c-45e8-83df-67ba73dc4fbd</id><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><version>1</version></requirementsReference></requirementsReferences><responsibleParties><responsibleParty ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Responsibility"><partyReferences><partyReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>b99b3d70-4f5f-4a54-85fa-4f989eb71970</id><type>cim.2.shared.Party</type><version>1</version></partyReference></partyReferences><roleCode>point of contact:</roleCode></responsibleParty></responsibleParties></numericalExperiment>