<forcingConstraint ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint"><canonicalName>HistoricalGHGConcentrations</canonicalName><conformanceIsRequested>True</conformanceIsRequested><description>What: Forcing data for concentration-driven historical CMIP6 runs. Here, we provide an outline of a consolidated set of atmospheric concentration time series for the long-lived greenhouse-gases, including CO2, CH4, N2O, HFCs, PFCs, SF6, several ODS, and NF3 to serve as input for the CMIP6 Historical simulations. 

Why: Depending on the model setup and emission species (short-lived, ozone, long-lived GHG), the historical simulation is driven by emissions and/or concentrations.</description><forcingType>observed</forcingType><keywords><keyword>Historical</keyword><keyword>Greenhouse Gas</keyword><keyword>GHG</keyword></keywords><longName>Historical Greenhouse Gas (GHG) Concentrations</longName><meta ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocMetaInfo"><authorReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><uid>253825f3-fbc8-43fb-b1f6-cc575dc693eb</uid><version>1</version></authorReference><createDate>2015-11-26 17:59:01.672460</createDate><id>4035d081-9174-418b-9707-251d5a1f90db</id><institute>--</institute><language>en</language><project>cmip6-draft</project><source>spreadsheet</source><type>cim.2.designing.ForcingConstraint</type><updateDate>2015-11-26 17:59:01.672460</updateDate><version>1</version></meta><name>Historical GHG Concentrations</name><references><reference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Citation"><abstract>Phase 6 of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP6) includes a Historical Simulation that serves as entry-check for other CMIP runs, spanning from 1850 to 2014.
Depending on the model setup and emission species (short-lived, ozone, long-lived GHG), this historical simulation is driven by emissions and/or concentrations. Here, we provide an outline of a consolidated set of atmospheric concentration time series for the long-lived greenhouse-gases, including CO2, CH4, N2O, HFCs, PFCs, SF6, several ODS, and NF3 to serve as input for the CMIP6 Historical simulations. The first published dataset is planned for May/June 2015 to be submitted to the GMD special issue, with a final version ready before 1 Jan 2016. This dataset will serve as basis for concentration-driven historical CMIP6 runs, the estimation of inverse historical emissions and as starting point for smoothly transitioning into future ScenarioMIP experiments.</abstract><citationStr>Historical GHG concentrations for CMIP6 Historical Runs</citationStr><context>Historical GHG concentrations for CMIP6 historical runs</context><title>Historical GHG concentrations for CMIP6 Historical Runs</title><url ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.OnlineResource"><description>Follow the link to the pdf</description><linkage>http://www.wcrp-climate.org/images/modelling/WGCM/CMIP/CMIP6Forcings_HistoricalGHGConcentrations_InitialDescription_150217.pdf</linkage><name>Historical GHG concentrations for CMIP6 Historical Runs</name><protocol>http</protocol></url></reference></references><responsibleParties><responsibleParty ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.Responsibility"><partyReferences><partyReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>3d01da3c-8b66-44ad-8f97-c25bb185f9f7</id><name>Malte Meinshausen</name><type>cim.2.shared.Party</type><version>1</version></partyReference><partyReference ontologyTypeKey="cim.2.shared.DocReference"><id>c9d23f5c-93f8-49db-9fbe-7fddc4209bc8</id><name>Alexander Nauels</name><type>cim.2.shared.Party</type><version>1</version></partyReference></partyReferences><roleCode>point of contact:</roleCode></responsibleParty></responsibleParties></forcingConstraint>